When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Nearly two million women in the U.S.
will enter menopause this year.
So what does the research tell us
about the best methods to alleviate
menopausal symptoms?
Here’s our first story.
Testosterone is linked
with sexual desire
in both men and women.
Women normally produce
testosterone
throughout the life cycle.
Although postmenopausal ovaries
continue to produce
testosterone,
levels naturally decline
with age.
Testosterone blood levels
decrease
approximately 50 percent
by age 50,
which may play a role
in the decline in libido
(using masturbation frequency
as a partner-independent proxy).
A syndrome of "female androgen
deficiency" symptoms
has been popularized,
but there is no evidence
testosterone "replacement"
helps with mood or well-being,
hot flashes,
or bone, cardiovascular,
or metabolic health.
The only evidence-based reason
to try testosterone
in postmenopausal women
is for the treatment
of low sexual desire
that causes distress.
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
of three dozen
randomized controlled trials
involving more than 8,000 women
found that
testosterone treatment
significantly increased
postmenopausal sexual desire.
The increase in frequency
of "satisfactory sexual events"
was statistically significant,
but not
clinically significant enough
to warrant FDA approval,
especially given
the uncertainty
about long-term side effects.
The women on testosterone
only logged a little under
one additional satisfactory
sexual event a month,
compared to placebo.
Currently,
there are more than 30
FDA-approved
testosterone products for men,
but none for women.
Clinicians can trial
a few months
of a male transdermal
testosterone preparation
at one-tenth the dose or less,
making sure to check levels
to prevent overdosing,
which can have
virilizing side effects,
such as clitoral enlargement
and voice changes.
Even at premenopausal
physiological doses,
testosterone can cause acne
and excessive hair growth
on the chin, cheeks,
and upper lip.
Unlike oral testosterone,
formulations administered
through the skin
don't appear to have
the same negative effects
on cholesterol levels,
but long-term safety data
for women
regarding cardiovascular,
cancer,
and cognitive outcomes
are lacking.
It has been estimated
that more than a fifth
of prescriptions
for male testosterone products
are actually written for women,
and this is not including
custom-compounded testosterone.
A consensus position statement
of international
medical societies
specializing in hormone issues
recommends against compounded
"bioidentical" testosterone
due to the lack of evidence
for efficacy and safety.
Similarly,
the dietary supplement DHEA,
which can convert
into testosterone
within the body,
cannot be recommended
for low libido in women,
since a meta-analysis
of more than 20
randomized controlled trials
found no significant effect
on improving desire
and sexual function.
Are there any natural ways
for women to raise
their testosterone levels?
Listening to music
for just 30 minutes
can increase testosterone levels
in young women
by about 20 percent.
Interestingly,
the opposite effect
was found in men.
For more
on the effects of music,
check out
my video Music as Medicine.
Heavy mint consumption
can lower testosterone levels
in both men and women.
There are case reports of men
drinking four cups (0.95 L)
a day of spearmint
or peppermint tea
losing their sex drive.
Given the apparent
anti-androgenic effects,
researchers decided
to try it out
on women concerned
about excessive hairiness,
and in a matter
of just five days,
were able to drop
their free testosterone levels
by about 30 percent
with two cups (0.50 L)
of mint tea a day.
There's a syndrome called PCOS,
or polycystic ovarian syndrome,
which can result in abnormally
high testosterone levels
in women,
which can be successfully
brought down with mint tea,
but for women
struggling with low libido,
it might not be
a good choice.
In my next story,
we look at the different health risks
of vaginal and oral estrogen.
I explained
how the first-line treatment
for mild to moderate vaginal dryness
due to menopause are lubricants
and moisturizers, and I called out
the safest brands.
If over-the-counter lubricants
and moisturizers are insufficient
to control the genitourinary
symptoms of menopause, low-dose,
local estrogen therapy
is recommended,
unless women have a history
of hormone-dependent cancers
like endometrial or breast.
Local, meaning applied vaginally,
as opposed to taken orally.
Vaginal application is considered
safer and more effective
than systemic hormone therapy.
A meta-analysis of 58 studies
comparing vaginal
to systemic estrogens
found that vaginal estrogen therapy
offered better symptom relief
than estrogen pills, patches, or implants.
In fact, many women who are on systemic
menopausal hormone therapy
have to add on supplemental vaginal
estrogens to control symptoms.
Vaginal estrogens are available
as a variety of creams,
suppositories, and rings.
Thirty randomized, control comparative
trials have been performed,
and there appears to be
no difference in efficacy
between the various preparations.
However, they may take weeks
before a noticeable alleviation
of symptoms is detected,
and two to three months
before the full effect is achieved.
Although year-long studies
can clearly demonstrate
vaginal estrogen’s benefit,
studies as long as 12 weeks
have failed to manifest
superiority to placebo.
Some of the estrogen applied
to the vulva or vagina
is systemically absorbed
and therefore convey
the same black box FDA notice
that oral estrogens carry,
an all-caps warning of increased risk
of “endometrial cancer,
cardiovascular disorders, breast cancer
and probable dementia.”
Vaginal estrogen
is considered safer, though,
since it can be used
at a much lower dose
(as low as one-hundredth the oral dose).
The Harvard Nurse’s Health Study
did not find any increased risks
associated with vaginal estrogen use
over 18 years of follow-up.
Randomized controlled trials
lasting up to a year
appear to confirm its safety,
but there have been observational
studies linking vaginal use
to about a doubling of odds
for endometrial cancer,
but this was done
back in the 1970s
when higher estrogen doses
were used.
And a more recent study out of Denmark
that found the same thing
may have been confounded
by concurrent oral estrogen exposure.
Out of an abundance of caution, though,
even low-dose localized estrogen
may be contraindicated
in hormone-dependent cancer survivors
to be on the safe side.
Breast cancer survivors
suffering from GSM
may want to consider
vaginal DHEA instead.
Oral DHEA doesn’t appear
to offer any benefit,
but in 2016 the FDA approved vaginal
DHEA suppositories for pain
during intercourse due to menopause.
It’s converted locally into estrogen
and does not significantly
affect systemic hormone levels.
A downside is that it has to be
administered nightly,
whereas estrogen preparations
are typically twice a week,
or even every few months
with the vaginal rings.
For those who would rather
have an oral treatment,
there is ospemifene,
a tamoxifen-type drug
that has pro-estrogenic effects
on the vaginal lining.
However, it can actually double
the rate of hot flashes
and urinary tract infections
in the short-term,
and insufficient data is available
for long-term safety.
Finally today,
we look at what behaviors
or circumstances
cause variability in the
onset of menopause.
Since 1970,
the proportion of women having
their first child after age 35
increased nearly tenfold.
This may introduce a "longevity
penalty" on their children,
as those born to older mothers
don't tend to live as long,
but mothers
having children later
tend to live longer themselves.
For example,
female centenarians
were found to be
nearly four times more likely
to have had children
after age 40
than women
who died by their 70s.
This doesn't necessarily mean
delaying kids
will make you live longer.
Smoking, for example,
could be a confounder,
causing both early menopause
and an early death.
Or maybe
delayed reproductive aging
is just a sign
of slower aging in general.
However some have suggested the
biological changes of pregnancy
might have
a rejuvenating effect,
even going so far as to suggest
that parabiosis mechanism,
bathing in the blood of babies,
but just not in
a Countess Bathory sort of way.
To sort between
these possibilities,
researchers studied
the longevity
of brothers of women
who gave birth after age 45,
and that of their wives.
The brothers with late-fertile
sisters lived longer,
but their wives did not.
This suggests
a genetic robustness cause,
rather than
a rejuvenation effect,
and the fact
that the longevity benefit
didn't extend to their wives
suggests it's not due
to a confounder
like socioeconomic strata.
On the other hand,
women who experience
extremely early menopause,
the 1% who stop menstruating
by age 39,
may be at risk
for diminished longevity,
and should
therefore be counseled
to adopt a particularly
healthy diet and lifestyle.
Approximately half
of the variability
of age of menopause
between women
is explained by genetics.
Other than smoking,
what other behaviors
or circumstances
can help explain the rest?
Factors that don't appear
to affect the age of menopause
include exercise, obesity,
alcohol, coffee,
or vitamin D status.
Interestingly,
women who've been married
tend to arrive
at menopause later.
Some suggested it may be the
influence of male pheromones,
given the fact that exposure
to male armpit odor
makes women's cycles
more regular,
but it turns out
that male cohabitation alone
doesn't appear to matter.
It may be the sex.
Married older individuals tend
to have more sex, and indeed,
pre- and peri-menopausal women,
average age 46,
who reported sex weekly
were 28% less likely
to experience menopause
over the subsequent decade
than those reporting sex
less than once a month.
You can very well imagine
how this could be a result
of reverse causation, though.
Instead of more sex
leading to later menopause,
a later menopause
may have instead led
to more sexual engagement.
The relationship between
tobacco use and early menopause
is thought to be mediated
by the toxic effects
on the ovaries
of the polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons in the smoke.
Among nonsmokers,
this PAH exposure
is almost entirely from food,
mostly grilled, barbequed,
and smoked meats.
Could this explain why,
in the Harvard Nurses'
Health Study II,
higher plant protein intake
was associated
with a significantly lower risk
of early menopause?
Feed female monkeys
a diet high in animal protein
and not only did they get
more atherosclerosis,
but also an acceleration
of ovarian aging.
Now, in the original
Harvard Nurses' Health Study,
animal protein consumption
was associated with infertility,
such that replacing even 5%
of animal protein intake
with plant protein
could potentially cut the risk
of infertility in half.
But in
the Nurses' Health Study II,
while plant protein
appeared to delay menopause,
animal protein intake
was not associated
with menopause age
either way.
And in
the UK Women's Cohort Study,
those eating more animal protein
were 6% more likely
to experience a later menopause.
The data is similarly
conflicting in vegetarians.
Some studies
found no difference
or a later age of menopause
in vegetarians,
but others found an earlier age
compared to nonvegetarians.
For example,
the largest study
found that vegetarians
reached menopause
at an average age
of 50.1 years
compared to nonvegetarians
at 50.7 years.
As I noted, premature menopause
before age 40
may be detrimental
for longevity,
but being a little earlier
within the normal range
may actually be beneficial
for cancer risk.
At the same age, breast cancer
risk is about 40% higher
in premenopausal compared
to postmenopausal women,
presumably due
to higher exposure
to the "necessary evil"
hormone estrogen.
Breast cancer risk
is 3% higher
for every year later
a woman starts menopause
and 5% higher
for every year earlier
a girl starts menstruating.
On average, women whose periods
hold off until age 15
appear to live the longest.
Vegetarian women tend to have
lower estrogen levels,
perhaps due
to higher fiber intake,
and interventional studies show
that switching
to a more plant-based diet
can reduce
circulating estrogen levels
by more than 40%.
This could explain
why vegetarian girls
may hit puberty later,
and why those eating
strictly vegetarian
not only have
lower cancer risk overall,
but particularly lower risk
for female-specific cancers.
Age of menopause
may not be a factor though,
based on
an interventional trial
randomizing women
on the verge of menopause,
average age 49,
to two years
of a lower fat diet
to reduce breast cancer risk.
The intervention group
ended up eating more fiber,
and therefore more plant-based,
but though they did
experience improvements
in mammogram findings,
the dietary shift
failed to influence
the timing of menopause.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.